Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
What is going on?
You should be ashamed to ask.
The woman your sister sent here
committed an utterly shameless act.
Is she truly the shameless one?
After all, it was not Noble Lady Lustré
who wrote this letter.
What letter?
This is what happened.
Last night, I asked Ruyi to bring some snacks
from the Imperial Kitchen.
She happened to see Xiao-Lezi,
the Third Prince's servant.
He was lurking around Long Street.
The Third Prince has always been prudent.
He's not that kind of person.
He's been prudent?
I'm afraid that's just a façade.
Your Majesty, please forgive my bluntness.
But you haven't educated your son well.
The Third Prince is young and lacks worldly wisdom.
This worthless wretch must have seduced him.
Your Majesty, I did not... I did not!
She was selected by Noble Prince Guo's estate.
No good can come from a lowly maid.
I believe that the Third Prince is innocent here
and has been framed.
But the messenger was caught red-handed.
The Third Prince wrote this letter himself!
This wretch must have first seduced him!
- But...
- Enough, stop arguing.
Your Majesty!
You cannot let your own son suffer such injustice!
Your Majesty, I truly didn't seduce the Third Prince!
You acted improperly and seduced an imperial prince.
I now grant you a way to end your own life.
Your Majesty, I didn't do it!
You have told me your whole story,
and I don't want to hear any more of it.
- Su Peisheng.
- Your Majesty.
Take her out and bestow her a length of white silk.
Yes.
- Your Majesty!
- You two, come here!
Your Majesty! Your Majesty!
I'm not guilty!
Your Majesty!
Your Majesty.
Enough!
I'm not guilty!
Hongshi has been kneeling since late last night
in Fengxian Hall [for Ancestor Worship].
This matter ends here.
I don't want to hear a word
of gossip in the palace.
Yes.
You two are dismissed.
I have a question for Noble Consort Lumière.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Did Lord Consort Yu select Noble Lady Lustré?
Yes.
Is it possible that...
someone arranged for Noble Lady Lustré
to seduce an imperial prince,
in order to usurp my throne?
Your Majesty, why do you ask?
Hongshi is my eldest son.
The court is hotly debating whether to name
him or a younger prince as the Crown Prince.
Destroying Hongshi's reputation
is the same as destroying mine.
Your Majesty, Yuyin would absolutely never dare to do that.
She would not, but what about
Noble Prince Guo?
I can vouch for him, too.
On what grounds do you vouch for him?
Everyone in this palace
experienced the chaos of the nine lords'
battle for the throne
and how terrifying the princes' lust
for the throne was.
Noble Prince Guo was one of the prior emperor's
preferred choices for Crown Prince.
Your Majesty is wise.
But Noble Prince Guo truly would not dare.
My concern is that
although he dares not do anything to me,
he could be using Lord Consort Yu's hands
to scheme against my sons.
All these years, Noble Prince Guo's heart has been
loyal and devoted to Your Majesty.
Loyal and devoted?
Who can gouge out his heart and prove that?
So, even though you and Noble Consort Estime
feel that I have wrongly convicted Noble Lady Lustré,
I have to protect the reputation of the imperial family.
I must protect my son.
I can't expose myself
to any potential manipulation.
Your Majesty,
Noble Lady Lustré has truly suffered injustice.
It was done for the Great Qing,
therefore it was not an injustice to have wronged her.
Since Yuyin is your honorary sister,
suspicion must be averted from you.
There have been so many trivial matters
in the palace lately.
Perhaps you're tired.
The Empress will take care of the palace affairs
and Noble Consort Estime will assist her.
Is Your Majesty...
suspicious of me?
The Empress is right.
As the mother of an imperial prince,
you cannot escape suspicion.
Imperial Father.
Two slaps:
One for coveting your Imperial Father's woman,
The other for coveting the Emperor's woman.
Imperial Father!
This is all my fault.
I beg for your forgiveness.
Of course I will forgive you.
Not only because you're my eldest son,
but also a son of the Aisin-Gioro Clan.
The prestige of the imperial family must be protected.
Yes, I admit my fault.
You admit your fault.
But someone else has shouldered the blame for you.
I have already executed Noble Lady Lustré.
She... she...
Of course she was innocent.
You're the one to blame.
But you are my son,
and I can't expose you to harm
just because of a woman.
I caused her death!
Yes.
You caused her death!
You forgot "the bounds of Heaven and Earth"
and "the moral ethics of human beings."
Imperial Father...
Stay here and reflect deeply on your wrongdoings.
If you make another mistake,
even I will not be able to save you.
Lumière.
It's so quiet here.
You can even hear the flowers falling.
Your palace is hardly ever this quiet.
No one in the palace is favored forever.
Once you realize this, there is nothing to fear.
Losing favor -
If you treat it as a torment,
then your life will be a torment.
If you face it calmly,
then your life will be calm.
Nothing matters but one's own state of mind.
When you get a chance, Estime,
could you offer incense to Noble Lady Lustré with me?
She is a pitiful soul.
All right.
It was all my fault.
My intention was to limit the Empress's power.
But I pushed too hard
and blame fell upon you and Noble Lady Lustré instead.
Noble Lady Lustré indeed suffered injustice.
Yet Noble Prince Guo was cast under
undue suspicion: a far greater injustice.
I never expected this.
His Majesty has never liked the Third Prince.
Yet he has protected him throughout this affair.
He showed a heavy hand in executing Noble Lady Lustré,
which has given the Empress a chance to bite back
and gain the upper hand.
His Majesty values prestige, so he always considers the good name of the imperial family.
No matter how much an heir misbehaves,
he is still the Emperor's son.
And in this instance, the designation of
the Crown Prince is also at stake.
Naturally, His Majesty is more cautious.
I made some of your favorite desserts.
I don't have much of an appetite.
What's the matter?
Perhaps I've had too many these days.
Jinxi, prepare a bowl of sour plum soup.
Yes.
You don't usually like sour food.
It's been a while.
I'm rather craving it now.
A good appetite is a blessing in itself.
Oh...
Lumière,
are you again...?
Ah, what wonderful blessings you have!
With this baby,
all our current difficulties will be resolved.
I will go inform His Majesty immediately.
This soothes my remorse over implicating you.
My difficulties aren't hard to resolve.
But I'm worried about Noble Prince Guo and Yuyin.
How has Noble Consort Lumière been these days?
The doctors say that Her Highness has been languid
due to disharmony between Spleen and Stomach.
Her Highness has been feeling aggrieved recently.
She's not to blame.
She's not?
So I am to blame?
I would not dare, Your Majesty.
I had my reasons for asking her those questions.
This morning,
Ortai and Maci had a heated debate.
Back and forth... still about
the designation of the Crown Prince.
Whether inside or outside the palace,
who knows how many people are
eyeing my Dragon Throne.
Announcing my chosen Crown Prince is sure to cause
"a tumult of chickens and dogs."
I should come up with a plan lest things go wrong.
Your Majesty is wise.
Noble Consort Lumière is now with child.
I do not wish to see her distressed.
It is strange
that all of the recent events have been targeting Noble Consort Lumière.
It is rather suspicious.
Not that I'm unaware.
The harem
seems tranquil on the surface
but murky waters lie beneath.
I intend to purify the waters.
But once you touch the bottom,
it is mostly women's concerns, unworthy of my time.
Empress Première's devotion to her sister has led me
to turn a blind eye in many situations
and the events pass.
In sum, trouble within the harem is nothing.
What I'm more concerned about
is collusion between the court and the harem
to plot against me.
I have no choice but to be wary.
Your Majesty is sage.
Deliver my desserts to the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
Let Noble Consort Lumière know
that I am thinking of her.
Yes. I will go right away.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Today is the fifteenth day of the month -
a grand occasion.
With His Majesty's incense offering,
our Great Qing will be peaceful and prosperous.
I haven't held the Sixth Prince for quite a while.
He's gained some weight.
The Sixth Prince has grown taller again.
Because of Your Majesty's care,
he wants to grow taller and stronger for Your Majesty.
I care for the princes and the princesses,
and of course I care for all of you.
The days are getting hotter.
Don't seek relief by eating raw or cold foods.
Don't stand in a draught when you're sweating.
I thank Your Majesty for your caring words.
I heard Noble Consort Lumière coughing when getting up this morning.
It made my mind ill at ease.
Noble Consort Lumière has always exerted herself.
If you cannot be helpful,
and instead cause her even a shred of worry,
that will upset me even more.
Yes.
There are a large number of servants in the harem.
Inevitably, that leads to gossip.
Starting with your own palace,
expel maids who come from the Han and Mongolian banners.
The maids from the Manchu banners
will take turns serving.
Yes.
Nevertheless, Your Majesty's close servants
should not be expelled.
I loathe servants who gossip.
First expel those who like to cause trouble
behind others' backs.
The Dzungars are now a rising threat on the borders.
Cutting spending within the palace, even small amounts,
demonstrates our support for the front lines.
You should all act appropriately.
I will obey Your Majesty's instructions.
- I want this.
- This one should be here.
Putting it here is better.
I heard servants are being expelled from all over the palace.
This is how His Majesty expresses his
displeasure with the Empress.
His Majesty's mind is unfathomable.
It's getting warmer.
I've noticed that you've been more reluctant to walk around.
Every day you seem fatigued and lethargic.
This pregnancy is a bit strange.
I'm prone to feeling nauseous, and my chest feels heavy and tight.
That wasn't the case when I had Longyue.
I suggest consulting Doctor Wei Lin.
Although you've given birth to children before,
it's always better to take extra care.
Noble Consort Estime is right.
Empress Première also experienced
much discomfort when she was pregnant.
Giving birth to a child is like
walking by "the Gate of the Ghosts."
Even though Empress Première was carefully attended to,
she and her child didn't escape death.
Nurturing a child in the palace is hard.
You've been so worried and preoccupied lately.
You should take better care of yourself.
I've become good at lazing around, but still feel unwell.
Sister, sister, chase her!
Sister, sister! Sister chased by sister!
Sister! Chase her, sister!
A sister... chased by her sister...
Give it to me, give it to me!
The Empress... killed by the Empress!
The Empress was killed by the Empress?
What did you say?
Even if you resent the Empress to the core,
you cannot say this out loud.
Quickly, take the prince and princesses away.
Go play outside.
You were saying who killed who?
The Empress was killed by the Empress.
The Empress...
Have you discovered something?
I wasn't speaking nonsense;
those were Lingrong's last words before she passed away.
I thought she was telling me
she was killed by the Empress,
and wanted me to kill the Empress for her.
With a scheming mind like hers, she could have
taken revenge with her own hands.
There was no need to entrust you with a dying wish like that.
I hadn't thought carefully about her words before.
Hearing Lingxi say "sister chasing sister"
made me think differently...
maybe...
Lingrong's words can be understood literally.
From the look on your face, it seems like
you‘ve had similar doubts for a long time.
Back when His Majesty was still a lord,
since Yixiu was the daughter of a secondary wife,
she was initially given the title of Lord Consort.
She was to be promoted as the primary wife
if she gave birth to a prince.
That was until one day,
It was decreed that Empress Première should come to the estate
to accompany her newly pregnant younger sister.
But when she came across His Majesty,
who could have imagined that
His Majesty would fall in love at first sight?
He immediately went to ask the Empress Dowager
to make Empress Première his primary wife.
Since His Majesty was so determined and earnest,
the Empress Dowager could not change his mind.
So His Majesty had never seen the Empress Première before that?
Never.
Since Their Majesties had made up their minds, and
because her elder sister was born with a higher status
Yixiu conceded that Première should become the primary wife.
So, Their Majesties breathed a sigh of relief.
Soon Yixiu gave birth to a prince,
but he had prenatal weakness and
passed away before reaching three years of age.
At that time, Empress Première became pregnant.
His Majesty had been favoring her exclusively
ever since she entered the family.
After Première conceived, His Majesty told Yixiu that
since she was well-versed in medicine,
she should take care of her elder sister
and assist the imperial doctors with their prescriptions.
Empress Première had all kinds of ailments during her pregnancy,
and suffered unusual and excruciating pain in labor.
She departed this world after leaving behind a stillborn child.
On her deathbed, she lay on His Majesty's knees and said:
"Please do not direct your anger
towards the imperial doctors,
and you must take care of my only sister, Yixiu."
Empress Première was kind to everyone in the estate.
But unfortunately, Heaven did not bless her with longevity.
Also...
I took a secret glimpse of the baby.
That child had quite a few blue spots on his body,
and had no breath at birth.
Blue spots?
Why did the baby have blue spots?
Does His Majesty know about this?
Yes.
The doctors said it was due to prenatal shocks,
resulting in weak blood and qi.
Because of the Empress's dying wish, the Empress Dowager agreed to make Yixiu the primary wife
instead of a woman from a different family.
You all know what happened after that.
Ula-Nara Yixiu valued the status
of being primary wife above all else.
Wouldn't she have harbored resentment
when someone robbed it from her?
She must have,
but unfortunately, we don't have any evidence.
During Empress Première's pregnancy,
it was Yixiu who served by her side.
It would have been possible for her to bribe
the servants and doctors on duty.
Usurpation...
fighting for favor...
destroying the child!
If she did this,
she was the one who murdered
Empress Première and the prince!
But... we don't have any evidence.
There must be evidence!
An Lingrong was by the Empress's side for a long time.
She had a most meticulous mind:
she must have discovered something.
Otherwise, she would never say such a thing.
Not necessarily.
We don't know if we're just overthinking.
I abhor her just as much as you do.
Nonetheless, if we cannot knock the enemy down in one blow,
we must endure with all our patience.
Longyue, why are you here?
Mother, I'm tired.
All right, we'll go in a moment.
This requires a long-term plan.
We cannot be careless.
Mother, what happened?
Don't worry.
I'm just thinking about how difficult this
pregnancy is for your mother Lumière.
She cannot eat much or sleep well.
It's so hard for her.
But I see other pregnant ladies like that too.
Longyue, did you know
your mother Lumière endured many hardships
when she was pregnant with you?
Her days were getting a little better,
when she became pregnant again.
I don't have the heart to watch her suffer.
Then I'll pay my respects to Her Highness in the evening.
Good. She'll be so happy to see you.
I want to make you happy too, Mother.
Imperial Father is always with Her Highness,
so I will spend more time with you.
What a good girl.
But the more favor your mother Lumière gains,
the more someone will want to harm her.
Therefore, Longyue, you need to promise me one thing.
Regardless of the situation,
you must protect your mother Lumière.
Don't let your Imperial Mother take advantage of her.
Mother, you've said this many times. I won't forget.
Doctor Wei, what is the matter with Her Highness?
She vomits anything she eats, and cannot sleep well.
What's happening?
May Your Highness calm your anger over my incompetence.
I would recommend bringing in Doctor Wen immediately.
He may be able to save this pregnancy.
[Eternal]
Your Majesty, the Palace of Eternal Longevity
has brought in Dr. Wen Shichu.
Is there something wrong with
Noble Consort Lumière’s pregnancy?
The Palace of Eternal Longevity has tightly sealed lips.
We can't get any information from them.
But when I inquired at the Imperial Infirmary,
they said all has been well.
Yet they have brought in Wen Shichu.
This pregnancy must be so important to her.
The anniversary of the prior emperor's birth
is the 8th day of the 3rd month.
Is everything ready?
His Majesty especially values filial piety.
I've asked the monks to chant and pray for seven days and nights,
and to handwrite copies of sutras
to be burned on that day for good wishes.
His Majesty is a filial son,
and so is his own son.
Is everything ready with the Third Prince?
The Third Prince will present his poem to His Majesty.
With so many days of effort,
I'm sure the Emperor will be pleased.
The princes usually show their filial hearts
merely by paying respects.
Every anniversary His Majesty is
engrossed in filial remembrance.
His heart will be touched easily;
the Third Prince won't need to prepare much.
By the way,
the Third Prince is not the most talented writer.
Remember to ask the teachers to assist him.
His shifu Wang is educated and knowledgeable.
He was assigned to the Third Prince by His Majesty personally.
This shows His Majesty's high regard for the Third Prince.
I hope so.
He is the eldest son.
His Majesty naturally holds great expectations for him.
But Lady Lustré died...
this incident could implicate the Third Prince after all.
I will secretly contrive for high-status officials
to speak on his behalf.
Others will follow and he will gain public support,
earning His Majesty's trust and becoming the heir apparent.
He will. Nothing will hinder Your Majesty.
Your Highness, Dr Wen is here.
Peace and grace to Your Noble Highness.
Your Highness,
why do you look so pale?
I would not have troubled you
except as a last resort.
Please, Your Highness.
Your Highness,
I believe that Dr. Wei Lin has done his utmost.
Based on your pulse,
at this early stage, Wei Lin has detected
that your pregnancy
is more frail than normal.
So he has been using warm, stabilizing herbs
like huangqi and baizhu
to nurture Your Highness's health.
But unfortunately...
What is it?
At the beginning of Your Highness's pregnancy,
your heart was fretful and the qi of your organs was stagnant.
On top of that, giving birth to the twins caused a depletion of qi,
which had not yet recovered.
It was not a good time for conception.
So even if I try my utmost, I cannot turn the tide.
You can only keep the heir for as long as Heaven allows.
I need the truth.
How much longer can I keep my baby?
Your Highness has had this child for four months.
Even if Wei Lin and I exhaust all our medical skills,
the baby will not survive the fifth month.
The fifth month?
Yes.
Then my remaining time with my baby
is less than one month?
Your Highness,
Your Highness's health takes priority.
Your Highness will have
another baby in the future.
Please take care of your health.
Tell absolutely no one about this.
You and Wei Lin will do whatever you can
to keep my baby as long as possible.
Wei Lin always keeps two copies
of the prescriptions for my pregnancy.
One is archived in the Imperial Infirmary;
the other copy is here.
You should do the same.
In addition,
prepare a formula in advance
to let this child go.
Maybe one day,
this baby will bestow me a favor.
I see.
As long as it doesn't endanger Your Highnss's health,
I will do
anything you ask.
I am fatigued, you may leave now.
Yes, I will go prepare the medicine.
The Third Prince started assisting at Shang Shu Fang
[an academy for the princes].
Is everything all right?
All is well.
The Third Prince is prudent and respectful to his teachers.
The boy is a bit simple-minded, but has a good heart.
Yesterday, he told me that
he wanted to arrange a grand ceremony for
the prior emperor's birth anniversary.
He is filial indeed.
I agree with Your Majesty.
Where else does he normally visit, aside from Shang Shu Fang?
Aside from the academy and his own estate,
The Third Prince also likes to discuss
state affairs with the court officials.
He hopes to share Your Majesty’s burdens.
When you see Hongshi's tutor,
ask him to inform Hongshi
there has been no such custom
since the prior emperor's reign.
Yes.
Your Majesty, I have another topic to address.
Since there is a ritual to pray for the prior emperor,
we need to prepare the prior emperor's mausoleum.
Does Your Majesty want to visit it personally?
I have been feeling tired recently.
The Empress is also unwell.
Send a prince on my behalf.
May I request Your Majesty's decree on which prince will be sent?
So I can arrange with the Ministry of Rites.
There is no haste.
You'll know when I make a decision.
You may leave now.
I will obey Your Majesty's decree.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
I'll go to the Palace of Eternal Longevity
to visit Noble Consort Lumière.
Yes.
His Majesty is departing for the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
Your Noble Highness,
Dr. Wen brought the abortifacient herbs you requested.
He told me that
this medicine takes effect
immediately after you consume it.
I understand.
Your Highness, His Majesty will be here soon.
Please get ready.
Does my makeup look passable?
- His Majesty the Emperor.
- It looks good.
Peace to Your Majesty.
I have been busy with state affairs.
You look even more gaunt
than when I saw you two days ago.
It's all because of this naughty child in my belly.
Your Majesty didn't know
how he was tossing around in my belly all night.
I didn't sleep well.
This child is so active and playful,
he must be a healthy prince.
In the future, let me know if you can't sleep.
You'll have my company.
Your Majesty is busy with state affairs,
I dare not disturb your sleep.
The imperial heir is also a state affair.
I want you both to be safe and sound.
I have something to discuss with you.
What is it?
For the prior emperor's birth anniversary,
I want to send a prince to perform
the ceremony on my behalf.
Who do you think is most suitable?
In terms of both age and status,
the Third Prince is the most suitable candidate.
I certainly know that Hongshi is the most appropriate one.
He was my only son before Hongli and Hongyan were born.
Naturally I had high expectations of him.
However, the boy is obtuse and faint-hearted,
and has even been associating with officials privately.
During the final years of the prior emperor's reign,
there was great chaos
because many princes associated with officials
and plotted to usurp the throne.
How could he be so reckless?
The Third Prince is still young.
Naturally he cannot thoroughly consider his actions.
Your Majesty can simply point it out to him.
Even if I instruct him,
he already has his heart set on the throne.
Just like Yunsi, the former Eighth Prince.
No matter how our Imperial Father
advised or reprimanded the Eighth Prince,
it was futile.
The Third Prince is not like that.
He is the eldest among the princes.
It is inevitable that he thinks of himself
as my successor.
All right, I've thought it through.
You just take care of your health.
A giant coral has arrived in tribute from Qiongzhou Province.
It is very rare.
Tibetan Buddhism sees red coral
as an embodiment of the Tathāgata Buddha.
I think it will bring peace to your pregnancy.
If it is truly such a marvellous coral,
it would be a pity if I am the only one to admire it.
Why don't I invite all the concubines
to the Palace of Eternal Longevity
to appreciate it together?
If you like.
It's good timing.
The priests at Baohua Hall
made some talismans for my baby.
They said that these talismans will be effective
if people of the highest status in the harem
place them in the lucky sachets
and fasten them to my bed.
I think the most appropriate people, of course,
are the Empress, the Imperial Noble Consort,
and Noble Consort Estime.
And I will tie one myself.
That covers the four corners of the bed.
This will accumulate Heaven's blessings.
They surely will not refuse.
Her Majesty doesn't go out nowadays,
and has turned down many invitations.
But if Her Majesty doesn't come,
Heaven's blessing will be incomplete.
I will invite them, if you'd like that.
Why is the Empress still not here?
Your Majesty,
Her Majesty has already sent someone over,
saying that Her Majesty is not feeling well
and may not come today.
Why does she feel unwell when I invite her?
Maybe there's someone she doesn't want to see
in the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
So she feels unwell whenever she comes.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Go invite the Empress yourself.
She is the head of the harem -
it's inappropriate for her to be absent.
Yes.
Look, this red coral is dark red but translucent.
It is such a rarity.
Noble Consort Lumière is in great favor indeed.
Your Majesty is very considerate.
This coral is even more radiant at night.
This coral is rare, but the Heavenly thoughtfulness is rarer.
Your Majesty values Noble Consort Lumière
and bestows this coral to bring luck to her pregnancy.
I think the most touching thing
is Your Majesty's thoughtfulness.
Your Majesty,
could Her Majesty be upset with me?
She's not.
As the Empress, she must be magnanimous.
Your Majesty,
His Majesty sent Mr. Su to invite you.
Your Majesty has no choice now.
I know.
The Palace of Eternal Longevity has always
wanted to plot against me.
But I have no intention to step into such a
troublesome place.
But you have to consider His Majesty.
Her Majesty the Empress!
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
I respectfully greet Your Majesty.
May Your Majesty have grace and peace.
Rise quickly.
Yes.
You are in poor health.
Do you blame me for making you come?
How could I?
I was feeling unwell,
so I wasn't planning on attending.
But Your Majesty has been concerned about Noble Consort Lumière.
As husband and wife, we are of one heart.
How could I not care about her?
I'm late because I went to the repository
to find a statue of Guanyin Carrying a Baby
for Noble Consort Lumiere.
I hope that Noble Consort Lumiere
can give birth smoothly.
Jiang Fuhai.
Yes.
I thank Your Majesty for your care.
I will place this statue of Guanyin
in my chamber and offer incense day and night.
The Empress is virtuous.
Your Majesty, may I make a bold request?
Since Her Majesty is so caring towards the harem,
I wish to dedicate my coral to her, like
"offering a borrowed flower to the Buddha"
It is admirable that Noble Consort Lumiere
has such esteem for Her Majesty.
It's just that His Majesty gave you this coral
on account of your pregnancy.
I want for nothing.
Noble Consort Lumiere,
you should keep the coral for your own pleasure.
You must not disappoint the good
intentions of His Majesty and mine.
Your Majesty is benevolent.
Imperial Noble Consort and I are also here today
to pray for Noble Consort Lumiere's
timely delivery of another prince.
Noble Consort Lumiere,
have the priests delivered the talismans?
They're here.
Xiao Yunzi?
Your Highness.
Your Majesty,
the priests said that
both the talismans and lucky sachets can bring auspiciousness.
They can bless the baby in my belly
with safety and health.
But I must trouble Your Majesty and my two fellow consorts
to help me place the talismans into the sachets
and hang them by my bedside.
It's as "easy as lifting our hands."
Your Majesty, Noble Consort Lumiere is pregnant.
There is a fetal god guarding her chamber.
I am unwell.
And a stranger entering her chambers
will displease the fetal god.
That would be thoughtless of me.
Imperial Noble Consort and Noble Consort Estime
are willing to make such a small effort for my heir.
Why are you making every effort
to shirk your responsibilities?
You possess the Phoenix Seal:
you must bring harmony to the harem.
Since Noble Consort Lumière became pregnant,
Her Majesty hasn't visited the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
Your Majesty shouldn't see yourself as a stranger.
There are no concerns with Your Majesty visiting more often.
Noble Consort Estime is right.
Yes.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.